Jouy mss., 1793-1843 LMC 1565
Lilly Library
Jouy mss.
1793-1843
Lilly Library
Jouy, Étienne de, 1764-1846
Walker, Isabella.
Thiébault, Dieudonné, 1733-1807.
Thiébault, Paul-Charles-François, 1733-1807.
Hamilton, G.R.
Delmas, Antoine Guillaume, 1766-1813.
Thiébault, Adolphe, baron.
LMC 1565
1 Box 1 standard
The Jouy mss., 1793-1843, consists primarily of letters to and from soldier, journalist and librettist, Étienne de Jouy, 1764-1846.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 2002
Biographical Note
Étienne de Jouy, 1764-1846, was a French soldier, journalist and librettist. He was born on October 19, 1764 at Versailles. When he was 16, he joined the French army and sailed to South America in the company of the governor of French Guiana. He was then sent to India, but he returned home in time to participate in the French Revolution. Fighting with the Revolutionaries, Jouy attained the rank of adjutant-general. However, after falling under suspicion of treason, he was nearly captured in 1793 before moving to Switzerland in exile. Having abandoned his career as a soldier, Jouy turned to writing. The libretto for his first opera, La vestale, was published in 1807. Other operas and tragedies followed, including Fernand Cortez (1809), Pélage (1814), Bélisaire (1818), and Scylla (1821). Jouy's most famous work was the libretto for the opera Guillaume Tell (1829) with music by Gioachino Rossini. Jouy died on September 4, 1846 at St. Germain-en-Laye.
Scope and Content Note
The letters from Jouy himself are mainly to family members, with the earlier ones being to his fiancée, subsequently his wife, Isabella Walker. Later letters are to family members and to friends Dieudonne Thiébault and his son General Paul Thiébault (who married Isabella's sister Betsey), G.R. Hamilton, General Delmas, and others. Most of the letters and other documents are in French.
Subjects of the letters include Jouy's military, journalistic and theatrical careers, including the operas La Vestale (1807), Pélage, and Guillaume Tell (1829), and his tragedies Belisaire and Sylla, as well as matters relating to family news, current affairs, publishing and appreciations of Jouy. Also present are a few documents relating to his military promotions and his appointment as editor of La Publiciste in 1807.
Arrangement
The file was arranged, dated in and in some cases annotated by Jouy's nephew Baron Thiébault. The first folder contains the index prepared by Thiébault, with a title page inscribed: "Lettres de Monsr de Jouy, mon oncle, arrangées par moi, à Versailles, 89 avenue de St.Cloud, en juillet et août 1873. Baron Thiébault."
Related Material
See Thiebault Family mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Librettists --France --19th century --Correspondence.; Dramatists, French --19th century --Correspondence.; Journalism; Theater; Jouy, Étienne de, 1764-1846.; Jouy, Étienne de, 1764-1846. --Belisaire.; Jouy, Étienne de, 1764-1846. --Sylla.; Spontini, Gaspare, 1774-1851. --Vestale.; Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868. Guillaume Tell.; Thiébault, Adolphe, baron.
- Correspondence index for the years 1793-1843, written in, 1873, Jul-Aug. (Box 1)
- 1793, Jan-Apr. (Box 1)
- 1793, May-1794 (Box 1)
- 1795, Jan.-Jun. (Box 1)
- 1795, Jul.-[1804] (Box 1)
- 1805-1814 (Box 1)
- 1815-1821 (Box 1)
- 1822-1824 (Box 1)
- 1825-1828 (Box 1)
- 1829-1831 (Box 1)
- 1832-1837 (Box 1)
- 1838-1843 (Box 1)